why were one of the points that you
mentioned that I thought was so
important even though you only mentioned
it briefly as you said we're not the
last turn on the spiral right there's
this universal human and future stages
predicted and implicit in the way you
were talking about it was this parental
energy this birthing the future that you
talked about so often it really comes
through the reclaiming of your
motherhood Parenthood in global humanity
wide kind of fashion mm-hm and as we
were talking about in the last session
part of becoming fully human is becoming
fully adult which includes
this parental energy extending beyond
whether it includes our biological
children or not extending to the future
of humanity as a whole and how to really
engage that fully take responsibility
for it which extends back to the
thinking seven generations ahead kind of
concept and taking responsibility for
wanting our kids just like with our
biological kids wanting them to not just
have everything we had but to have more
to transcend us to go beyond and to set
up a situation for that and to now
really be thinking about that globally
for the first time ever because seven
generations ahead was tribal in
previously and we get to think about it
globally and that requires for them to
have that opportunity not just to care
for them but for the Commons that
supports them that's such a huge topic
it is and you know we talked about the
feminine co-creator and one of the thing
about the feminist she gives loves to
give birth and when the birth is
happening it's a mess but she has this
innate hope for what's coming when you
would look at the world right now it's
not so hard to have innate hope if you
think of what's being created it really
is an amazing slight flip of attention
because we're almost always noticing
what's not working so I think that it's
not even thinking seven generations
ahead the way I feel about it it's our
generation because we're all here and we
don't have seven generations to go like
we're going therefore it's very similar
to her birth when the time is
the birth it's going to be born what's
going to happen it's going to happen in
the next 10 to 15 years it's not many
many generations ahead so I'm thinking
of the fastest thing that could be done
that would make this shift the most
gentle birth possible and that would be
connecting what's creative but you know
this generation yeah connecting there's
kind of two pieces here and that are
we're talking about one down there
talking about the other and in your
presentation which was so wonderful you
focused on the kind of the emergent
social synergy that's here right now I
did right and Daniel you're pointing
kind of towards the future right and you
know I'm gonna start with the future
then go into into kind of our unique
self book and the socials with the
social synergy there's there's an old
text which is one of those elusive
Aramaic text that you know when I can't
fall asleep I I look for you know
instead of Prozac kind of helps you get
through the day yeah which talks about
why Abraham is the first covenant apart
nur right in the kind of classical you
know biblical story you know cuz after
Noah was a competitor and Adam was a
competitor and Abram gets the job mm-hmm
and and the elusive tech suggests that
he gets the job because he has the first
person have a grandchild right right
that he's actually able to transmit his
values to generations which is this very
powerful ability you know he creates the
beginning of this kind of covenantal
community that actually moves through
the generations yes so that's one kind
of movement one kind of covenant that
moves across the generations and in some
sense the only we could think of right
was how to how to cross generations how
to link generations now the kind of
looking you're talking about has that
old linking of generations but then it
has this linking right now between all
the different dimensions that exist in
earth today right right between all the
different creative forces whether they
exist and how do we bring right the kind
of leading-edge you know creative
emergent you know minds hearts right
together in this new higher synergy yes
so that's those are two to two pieces
and they need
each other and they need each other and
they need each other and they need each
other so I'm gonna cuz maybe suggest a
third piece of the matrix and we'll get
a Holy Trinity you know going and I
think this pieces is critical because
without it I can't quite see how it will
happen which is we also need to link
together it used to be that in the
different generations you at different
levels of consciousness right see if you
use like Kepler's model you know you
kind of move through different levels of
consciousness throughout as history
emerges and cultural evolution but today
around the globe we have all the
different levels of consciousness around
the globe right now yes right and so we
actually have to link those different
levels of consciousness that is to say
and it's part of what we try we're
trying to do here in these weeks we need
to create a story in which the the the
biblical right thinker has a place the
person in Islam has a place right the
Christian has a place the agnostic has a
place we need to create a story which
which doesn't pander to we don't to go
backwards we're not gonna be regressive
we're not gonna be homophobic we're not
gonna be up no eccentric but for example
we'll find what are the common deep
structures that allow us all have a seat
at the table so for example taking
sacred texts seriously that's something
that we can do and you're doing such
important work about how we can from an
evolutionary perspective evolve sacred
texts yeah taking sacred texts seriously
ritual notions of obligation right how
do we actually reclaim obligation
reclaim ritual right reclaim right we
have got to actually reclaim the core
structures right that actually are
emergent and actually transcend that
include because otherwise we risk right
and I think that's definitely not what
we're doing but I think it's a lot of
what our human potential movement does
is it transcends and excludes
right it kind of it kind of it doesn't
recognize what comes before it which
both lacks humility and reverence which
is always a bad idea but it's also
inaccurate and you can't actually build
a synergistic structure unless everyone
can find a way to have a seat at the
table I think this is very true and what
I discovered in doing the twenty five
synergistic convergence conferences and
inviting people that were specifically
of different levels right
from welfare mothers and gang leaders to
police officers and gene roddenberry
I mean I'm all up but what I found was
something that almost everybody had no
matter what level they might be in in
terms of the evolution of the spiral
dynamics is they had something they
wanted to create mmm and when that was
as honestly and legitimately from them
and they needed to give something and
they were recognized as people rather
than categories or organizations you did
not come in as a category or
inauguration you really came in I to say
are you satisfied with the way things
are going for you okay no he said yes
they got in because they said no not
satisfied right so then would you like
to be more satisfied with the way
they're going yes how about trying
something new what do you want to create
and what do you need to create it I mean
there was one labor leader in Los
Angeles who was really a tough guy mean
nasty didn't it was rude to me does the
idea of doing anything like this and so
I asked him if he was sad no it's there
but he said if I would tell the truth
they'd think I was a communist so I said
well what is the truth for you Wow I
have these great ideas he started to
tell me his ideas of creation they were
so much different than that personality
so I'm very loath to judge people by
being part of the category as long as
you get them in the game of what do you
want to create what do you need and what
do you want to give it's a special
talent and I wonder I mean I will just
ask this whether we can jump over some
of these differences by asking people a
question of their creativity rather than
their their interests or who they are
thinking look think they are or the
values they're espousing I think it may
be a new question that makes a
difference maybe it's a play with us for
a second - Daniel right in other words
when a person wants to create right the
the movement to creativity which is so
deeply shared across you know all levels
of consciousness nonetheless that
movement to creativity is interpreted
through right just like love is but love
is it interpret through a prism of
consciousness and so we need to invite
people always from wherever we are to
evolve consciousness and make evolve in
consciousness the name of the game and I
think the word you said is the key which
is dissatisfaction
it's always the place that you're
dissatisfied which is the technology of
growing up you only grow up when when
your worldview right is dissatisfying
either your own experience of being
alive in the world or your own
experience of the larger world being
functional so to actually address
people's dissatisfaction and then invite
them to kind of jump a level of
consciousness I think we can do that and
I think creativity is the starting point
if we create a vision in which people
can find a place at the table that's
right like that yeah that those things
together does that make sense it does it
does and the vision is really a question
to write what would it be like if what
you want to create we're further created
and asking other people for what you
need in order to do it a vision emerges
right Piru what's exciting to me about
this question you asked and what
happened in those sim cons as a result
of it is that not only is really asking
about people's creative impulse
something that's kind of missing from
almost any system of personal
development being adequately emphasized
but it really does have the potential to
if not leapfrog at least accelerate some
really significant kind of social
synergy and just stages of evolution
accelerates a good word here I think
it's an accelerator I think it also
fills in missing pieces cuz therapy as
critical as it is that focuses on our
broken parts if that's not going toward
something it's missing something huge
right and meditation if it's a system of
focusing on being present is important
but it's still missing that incarnated
as the creative impulse and personal
development education is creative keeps
being emphasized
it's it's like if you make that first
you actually make that primary and then
you do therapy where you have issues
that are getting in the way of your
creativity you do education and personal
development to get the skills necessary
for your creativity and that
historically we want to own all the
beautiful parts of it of our history
that marks talking about and
historically we've been separate right
been separate we're moving towards more
integration and when you ask the forward
oriented question in a way that doesn't
disown the past but also emphasizes the
future direction it's it moves us away
from the context of separate and into
the context of it when people are ready
to go when they're dissatisfied and now
we have a super dissatisfaction which is
collective you see we don't want to
forget it's different than when I was
doing the sin cons in the 70s now there
is a global dissatisfaction that we
might not survive this we can't forget
that and our spiral dynamics right right
right no no no I think that's right I
mean it just it's just kind of
clarifying to me now actually you know
in this conversation I've been thinking
for a long time and we talked about it
off offline yesterday but what the
technologies of growing up we're talking
about waking up growing up showing up
right we want to show up as unique self
and as our unique expression of the
evolutionary impulse yeah and unique
self home run over solace create us
right you know we want to wake up to the
fact that we're not separate right as
Daniel is gonna point us towards again
and again and we've all been talking
about then we want to show up you know
with psychological maturity with higher
and higher levels of consciousness which
is kind of that those levels of
consciousness which you're suggesting
well you know you're looking for a way
and I think I can feel that gorgeous
dark can we skip over kind of how do we
how do we write and that's what we're
looking for and it could be and I think
we're really onto something which is
maybe really critical here what moves a
person out of mythological consciousness
and when we say mythological of course
just for our friends listening you know
we mean let's say classical great
religions you know before let's say
democracy and rational Western
enlightenment emerges what moves a
personnel so what moves a person out is
two things either dissatisfaction with
the mythological level you know you
dissect the human body in the
Renaissance looks like there's a
different amount of bones than you
thought right you know Copernican
revolution
dissatisfaction and there's this really
exciting new party in town and the new
party is called science democracy third
person so it's that new party in town
that is so intoxicating that it moves
you out so what we're suggesting in
effect is that the new party in town
right is the unique self in the
evolutionary impulse yes that the
intoxication of that real party becomes
that right that joining becomes becomes
the the technology of growing up so
we're growing up not just because we're
dissatisfied with yesterday which we
were but we're actually being attracted
just like democracy and science
attracted us to move from the
mythological to the rational so now to
move from kind of pluralistic human
potential to a deep integral
consciousness right this this new vision
we're talking about all week the strange
attractor again becomes unique self in
the evolutionary impulse and the
excitement of it the excitement and the
innate passion to express innate passion
expression that's as innate as sexual
attraction you know that goes via all
categories yeah well I think the
attraction to create is going to be as
as ubiquitous as the sexual attraction
to procreate
now that's a big statement but but it's
who we are
ya know it's who we are it's who we are
implicit when you're talking about the
social synergy engine it's really
interesting that as much as synergy
seems like a communion principle in
terms of agency and communion communion
without differentiation is totally
uninteresting you don't get synergy
right right because to bring a bunch of
homogeneous things together it's the
same as they were separate you only get
synergy when you've differentiated and
then integrated so synergy actually is a
word that includes both which Marc
always points out about uniqueness right
that uniqueness is not just an agency
side of the word that it only emerges
out of a communion context and it's only
meaningful in the communion context so
we all have this deep impulse to have
something unique to offer and unique to
offer somebody and with other somebodies
and so this is looking at how do we you
and implicit in that new structure is
how do we get clear on what we uniquely
have to offer and then how do we get
clear on what the other uniqueness is
are that are
to come together in this a social
synergy so it's both of those together
and it's not interesting with either
side of it alone it's both end and and I
discovered that social synergy is a form
of social love it actually turns into a
love affair I mean it doesn't matter how
they start out if the person is
discovering that what he or she wants to
give and create is needed by others and
others need them they turn on a
different energy and I really believe
the psychology of synergy has not really
been explored which really no I'm that
that really brings us I mean to
concluding you know session 7 and you're
really in you know when we talk about in
session 8 is what's the erotic or
synergistic love or force of pleasure
right you know and if that famous quote
from detian are done there's an almost
sensual longing yeah you know that
almost sensual longing direct to be in
communion with those who are
participating the evolution of
consciousness it was of course referring
to exactly what you're referring to this
kind of essential strange attractor
right this your phrase tell erotic yeah
it's strange attractor right towards our
own arousal as homer and of ourselves
unique cells and this is an example the
three of us right this is three
different very different people coming
together in a synergistic environment to
co-create more than we could possibly do
alone oh my god that's what happens yeah
oh my god and in the next session what
we're gonna talk about is how we
actually map our way towards what dish
are done called that sensual longing to
create right the new world be with us